Grant Family Papers, 1778-1913
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Grant family papers
1778-1913
1830-1870
Grant family
MS 66
5 boxes (2.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Grant family papers include correspondence, diaries, account books and financial/legal papers, biographical and genealogical material, printed material, dating from 1778 to 1913. Topics include education, maintenance of Connecticut homestead, banking in Ohio, starting businesses in Nebraska and Illinois, and accounts of Mary Grant's experiences as a missionary in India and her death from cholera.
The Grant family Papers represent three generations, including educators, missionaries, a banker, pioneer lawyer, social reformer, writer and lecturer. Zilpah Polly Grant Banister, 1794-1894, was born in Norfolk, Connecticut. She was a pioneering educator and founder of Adams Female Seminary in Derry, NH, 1824, and Ipswich Female Seminary with Mary Lyon, 1827. She married William Banister, 1841. Her brother, Elijah Grant, was a town officer, who married Elizabeth Phelps Grant, 1809-1875. They had 8 children. Elijah Phelps Grant was a lawyer, philosopher, social reformer, and banker in Carleton, OH, and John Grant a teacher at Yale and founder of his own private school. Other family members were bankers, homesteaders in CT, pioneers in Nebraska and Illinois. Mary Z. Grant Burgess was a missionary in India.
It is clear from their content and their provenance, however, that they are actually the papers of her brother Elijah Grant, his wife Elizabeth Phelps Grant, their children, and the descendents of the eldest son, Elijah Phelps Grant. The correspondence consists mainly of letters exchanged within the family from the l830s to the l860s. Most of Zilpah Grant's letters were written to her nephews Marcus and John after she had married and given up teaching. John Grant, who taught at Yale and later established his own private school, sought her counsel as a former school principal. Correspondence of other family members relates to such topics as the maintenance of the original Connecticut homestead, banking in Canton, Ohio, and the starting of businesses in Nebraska and Illinois.
The early financial records, beginning in the l770's, are mostly from the settlement of the estate of Elijah Grant's uncle Samuel Cowles, of Colebrook, Connecticut, who died in l843. Account books belonging to Elijah Grant (l822-56) Elijah P. Grant (l866-67), James M. Grant (l868); Jennie Wallace (l890-97) and William Wallace (l90l-07) add to the fragmentary family financial record.
Notebooks, lectures, essays, and newspaper articles by Elijah P. Grant span the period from his college days at Yale to old age. One of his college notebooks contains transcriptions of letters describing the death of Mary Zilpah Grant Burgess who died of cholera in India where she and her husband were missionaries. The balance of the collection consists of diaries, a few photographs, compositions, and legal papers relating to various family members.
Portions of the Grant Family Papers have been digitized for the Five College Digitization Project Web site.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Grant Family Papers were a gift of Mary R. Wallace, descendant of the Grant family, in 1959.
Search Terms
Colebrook (Conn.)--History--Sources; Educators--New England--Biography--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Missionaries--India--Biography--Sources; Norfolk (Conn.)--History--Sources; Bannister, Zilpah P. Grant (Zilpah Polly Grant), 1794-1874; Grant, Elijah Phelps, 1809-1875; Adams Female Academy (Derry, N.H.); Burgess, Mary Zilpah Grant; Cowles family; Grant family; Grant, John; United States--Social life and customs--18th century--Sources; Frontier and pioneer life--United States--19th century--Sources; United States--Social life and customs--19th century--Sources; Women--Education--History--19th century--Sources; Yale University - Students--History--19th century--Sources; Lawyers--United States--Biography--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional Grant family papers are located in the Adams Female Academy Records and papers of Zilpa H. P. Grant Banister at Mount Holyoke College Archives, South Hadley, Massachusetts.
Portions of the Grant Family Papers have been digitized for the Five College Digitization Project Web site.
Bibliography
Additional biographical information on Zilpah Polly Grant Banister can be found in Notable American Women, 1607-1950; a biographical dictionary. Edward T. James, editor (1971).
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical and genealogical (Box 1, Folder 2)
    These documents are available online as part of the Five College Digitization Project Web site.
  - Bills, receipts, accounts, 1812-1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, deeds, quit claims, etc., 1795-1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1870-1872 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lake Erie Female Seminary, Painesville, Ohio (Mary Grant material), 1859-1860, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - To Grant family from friends, 1821-1891 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Banister, Zilpah Polly (Grant) to family, 1855-1874 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grant, Abigail (Cowles) (Mrs. Joel) to family, 1847-1877 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grant, Caroline (Mrs. Daniel) to family, 1854, 1869, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grant, Elijah to Dr. Phelps, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grant, Elijah Phelps to family, 1830-1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grant, Elizabeth to Martha Grant, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Grant, Gertrude D. (Mrs. John) to family, 1857-1860, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Grant, Jane (Jennie) to family, 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Grant, Joel to parents and brother, 1839-1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Grant, Joel to family, 1860-1873 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Grant, John to parents, 1848-1867 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grant, John to Martha Grant, 1842-1843 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grant, John to Marcus Grant, 1843-1864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grant, John to Marcus Grant, 1865-1877 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Grant, John to Zilpah P.G. (Grant) Banister, 1846-1852 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Grant, John to Zilpah P.G. (Grant) Banister, 1853-1858 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Grant, John to Gertrude Day Grant and friends, 1850, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Grant, Martha to Marcus Grant, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grant, Mary to Susan Boyd and Mrs. James Boyd, 1835, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Grant, Susan (Boyd) to Elizabeth and Lewis Boyd, 1837-1855 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Grant, Susan (Boyd) to Elizabeth Boyd (sister), l856-l869 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Grant, Susan (Boyd) to Elizabeth Grant, 1840-1859 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Grant, Susan (Boyd) to Jane M. Boyd (mother), 1831-1852 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Grant, Susan (Boyd) to William Grant, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hurford, Elizabeth (Grant) to family, 1853-1863 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Wallace, Mary (Grant) to family, 1853-1864 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Wallace, William, misc. correspondence to and from him (includes some other types of material), 1857-1913 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- FINANCIAL MATERIALS
  - Samuel Cowles
    - Account book, 1840-42 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Deeds, receipts, bills (many from the estate of Samuel Cowles), 1788-1850, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
  - Elijah Phelps Grant
    - Account books (2), 1822-42, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Account book, 1833-37 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Account book, 1833-56 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - James W. Grant: account books (2), 1868 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Isaac Jacklyn: receipts, indenture papers, deeds (many from his estate), 1856-1874 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- MISCELLANEOUS
  - Elijah Phelps Grant
    - College notebooks (Yale)
      - Memorandum Quotidiana and notes on the Class of 1830, 1828 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Chemistry with B. Silliman, Botany, and "An Account of the Death of Mrs. Mary Burgess…," 1828, 1842 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lectures
      - "What is the best mode of teaching reading?" 1838 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - "The Immortality of the Soul," 1849 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - "The Eternity of the Universe," 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "All Things Eternal," 1867 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Original Manuscripts," undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Notes and writings, miscellaneous, 1872, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Daguerreotype, Canton, Ohio, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - John Grant: Journals (2), 1854-1855 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dorothy Wallace: reminiscence and diary, "Omaha in the '80s" after 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jennie Wallace
    - Account book, 1890-97 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Composition book, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - William Wallace
    - Account books (2), 1901-1907 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Journals (2), 1857, 1860 (Box 5, Folder 5)